MATT SICKER

mattsicker@apache.org https://musigma.blog/ 847-736-8133

A software engineer and craftsman working on fast data and big data applications with a focus on functional programming, reactive streams, reactive microservices, architecture, devops, and development. Loves learning about and evangelizing new technology and refining existing tech. Expert in Scala and Java, and experienced or familiar with several other languages and platforms. PMC Chair of the Apache Logging Services project, member and assistant secretary of the Apache Software Foundation, contributor to several open source projects outside the ASF, board member of the Illinois Java User Group, technical blogger, and speaker at conferences and meetup groups. Long time advocate of free/libre and open source software.

Experience

Mar 2018 – Now

Assistant Secretary, Apache Software Foundation

• Files and maintains ICLAs, CCLAs, software grants, and other submitted forms.

IPMC Member, Incubator, Apache Software Foundation

• Reviews and mentors projects undergoing incubation at Apache.

Dec 2017 - Now

Founder, MuSigma Consulting, Chicago, IL

- Founder and principle software engineer of MuSigma Consulting.
- Worked with consultants at Spantree to develop an Excel file format parser for StreamSets.
- Developed a Gatling-based Elasticsearch load testing framework and command line tool with Spantree.
- Developed an RxKotlin-based Elasticsearch fake data generator framework and command line tool with Spantree.
- Collaborated on writing SOWs for client work.
- Instructed a week long bootcamp on cloud native development with CloudTraining.io.

Oct 2017 - Now

VP Logging Services, Apache Software Foundation

- PMC Chair of the Apache Logging Services project.
- Reports to the ASF Board regarding the Logging Services project.
- Collaborates on Log4j, Chainsaw, Log4j Scala API, and Log4j Kotlin API.

Nov 2016 – Nov 2017 — Senior Consultant, SPR Consulting, Chicago, IL Software Engineering

- Developed an Apache Kafka Connect plugin to encode and upload Apache Parquet files to Amazon S3.
- Developed an Apache Kafka Streams application to monitor and automatically restart failed Kafka Connect tasks.
- Collaborated on an Apache Spark batch process for synchronizing a gold/silver HDFS/Hive data lake.
- Developed a Kafka Connect deployment plugin for a client's in house deployment tool.
- Collaborated on configuring, deploying, and automating an Apache Zeppelin data lake sandbox environment using Apache Spark, Amazon EMR, and other Hadoop technologies.
- Wrote internal engineering blog posts for a client regarding internal tooling.
- Hosted client lunch and learn sessions to demo new tech.
- Advised a client's open source committee on how to make internal projects open source.
- Developed an Akka Streams application to query, stream, and export large amounts of IoT sensor data from Apache Cassandra.
- Developed a Vert.x microservice for managing user-uploaded media files in a cloud provider agnostic fashion.
- Developed an Elasticsearch connection pooling library.
- Collaborated on a Spring Boot REST API service for monitoring and managing tasks regarding the state of wind turbines.

Developer Evangelism

- Logging from both a developer's and operator's perspective (both blog and talk at Chicago Java User Group, 9 Nov 2017).
- Scala for Java developers (talk at Illinois Java User Group, 11 July 2017).
- Using Akka and Scala to implement event sourcing and CQRS (blog post).
- Why use a microservices architecture (blog post).
- A proposal on reactive microservice security similar to federation (blog post).
- Spring 5, Reactor, and reactive streams (blog post).
- The Lagom framework for reactive microservices (blog post).
- Use of Apache Avro, Thrift, and alternatives to typical REST/JSON architectures (talk at Mulesoft Connect 2017).

2014 - Now

PMC Member, Logging Services, Apache Software Foundation

- Develops and collaborates on Log4j, Log4j Scala API, Log4j Kotlin API, and Chainsaw.
- Writes API documentation and user manuals.
- Maintains the Log4j plugin system.
- Performs release management.
- Added a Cassandra appender plugin.
- Maintains logging API bridges to other libraries.
- Presented at ApacheCon Denver 2014: Intro to Log4j 2.0.

2015 - 2016, 2013 - 2014 -

Senior Software Engineer, Peapod, Chicago, IL

- Member of the Webcenter division in Peapod responsible for the development and maintenance of our sister grocery store websites (Stop & Shop, Giant Foods, and Martin's Foods).
- Collaborated with project managers, QA testers, web developers, database administrators, system administrators, and other engineers to make a content management system integrated with various loyalty, coupon, and user account systems.
- Developed a modular, reactive, REST-driven integration API using Apache Camel, Karaf, ActiveMQ, Netty, Hazelcast, Spark, Hibernate, and various other supporting libraries.
- Developed a Spring MVC proxy application around our ESB to allow OAuth2-protected REST APIs to be used by our websites and mobile apps.
- Administered CentOS VMs that host these applications.
- Developed build and deployment infrastructure using Atlassian Bamboo and Docker.
- Developed a CMS using Oracle Commerce (ATG) on WebLogic.

2011 - 2013

Principle Software Engineer, Deep Dish Development, Mount Prospect,

- As one of two co-founders, I administered our cloud servers, databases, finances, and other paperwork.
- Set up and administered multiple GNU/Linux cloud virtual machines on AWS using Apache, MySQL, PHP, Ruby, and Java.
- Collaborated on developing corporate structure, business plan, and other documents.
- Performed code review and mentoring for other developers.

2011

Lead Programmer, LRH Advertising, Glenview, IL

- Migrated server from VPS hosting to AWS EC2, S3, RDS, and Route53.
- Developed a prototype Drupal-based social networking website for retirees.
- Administered Apache web servers and MySQL databases.
- Introduced the use of git for software version control.

2011

SEO Consultant, Lights America, Wheeling, IL

- Optimized page loading speed for various lighting showroom websites.
- Referred and mentored a full time web developer to maintain and improve existing websites.
- Migrated image hosting from on premises to Amazon S3 and CloudFront.

Skills

- Programming languages: Scala, Kotlin, Java, Go, Bash, Python, Groovy, Ruby, Lisp, C, C++, SQL, LTFX, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Haskell
- Frameworks: Akka, Kafka, Spark, Spring, OSGi, Camel, Vert.x, Reactor, RxJava, Hibernate, ATG, Karaf, Tomcat, Jetty, ActiveMQ, ZeroMQ

- Databases: PostgreSQL, MySQL, MariaDB, Oracle RDBMS, Cassandra, Hive, Elasticsearch, SQL Server, MongoDB
- Tools: Git, Subversion, Gradle, Maven, Ant, SBT, Make, Docker, Mesos, Jenkins, Travis CI, Bamboo, Jira, GitHub, BitBucket, GitLab

Education

- Roosevelt University, 2010 2012, studied mathematics and computer science.
- Oakton Community College, 2007 2009, studied mathematics and computer science.